I see. So, Canute is dead?
そうか。クヌートは死んだか
No. He went missing, to be precise.
いえ。正確には行方不明とのことです
Ragnar's unit tried to rescue Canute,
ラグナル隊はクヌート王子の救出を試み、
and engaged Thorkell in battle at Marlborough.
マールバラにてトルケル軍と交戦。
In the midst of the confusion,
混乱の中、
His Highness the Prince went missing.
王子殿下の消息も途絶えました
Then aren't they still surrounded by Thorkell's men?
ほう…ではいまだトルケル軍に囲われておるのではないか？
Yes. However, we didn't see anyone among
Thorkell's men
はっ。ですが…その後2日間、
who looked like he could be the prince for two days.
殿下とおぼしき姿は敵軍中に認められずとのことです
He may still be alive and is waiting for help.
生き延びて救助を待っておるやもしれんが…
However, even if we were to send help,
助けを送るとしても
we'd have to wait until spring.
春まで待たねばならん
I'm sure you must be very worried,
王陛下におかれましては、
Your Highness.
ご心中いかばかりかと…
If Canute
クヌートがもし…
had been as talented
兄のハラルドを上回る器量を
as his brother Harald,
持ち合わせていたならば
he might not have
ended up missing.
行方知れずになどならずに済んだかもしれんな
Wow! It's snowing!
あぁ…雪が降る…
AFTER YULE
The war is ending!
戦争が終わる…
Winter.
冬よ…
DECEMBER 1013
GLOUCESTER, EARLDOM OF MERCIA
お前は戦士の心さえ凍らせるのか…
You're cold enough to freeze even a warrior's heart.
Oh, winter!
おお冬よっ！
Captain. Roasted pork or boiled pork.
What do you want?
大将～！焼き豚と煮豚どっち食うー！？
Give me both!
両方！
I can't understand you. Swallow your food first.
わかんねーよ。まず飲み込め
Okay.
あい
In any case,
やー…なんだかんだ言ってさー。
the fact that the prince escaped was a big loss to us.
あそこで王子に逃げられたのはイタかったなァ
He didn't escape! You handed him over.
いやいや。あんたが渡したんだろ
That prince was a coward,
but he could have been useful.
あの王子は腰ヌケだけど使い道はあったんだよな
We could have put him on a pedestal
and started a new dynasty.
あれを担ぎ上げて新王朝旗揚げとかよォ。
It would have helped gather soldiers for an army
at least.
兵隊集めるだけでも効き目あるぜ
If you're the one who's going to carry him,
ま…あんたがみこしの担ぎ手なら、
you'd be pretty powerful.
ちょっとした勢力になりそうだな
Indeed. What?
だろ？
Hey, you! English girl!
おーい！そこなイングランド娘！
Yes?
はぁい！
Beer! Bring a keg!
ビール！タルで持ってきて！
Excuse me! They ordered another keg!
すいませぇん！ビール、タルで追加ですゥ！
Another one? Damn!
またか！クソォッ！
Those rascals! They're going to eat through
the entire city!
おのれぇならず者どもめ！この町を食い尽くす気か！？
This is robbery!
これじゃあ略奪と大差ないっすよぉ…
Stop crying!
泣くな！
If I was going to lose the prince anyway,
I should have given him to the English instead.
どーせ王子とられんだったらイングランド軍にくれてやってもよかったなぁ
What?
あ？なによ？
You're so difficult.
困った人だなあんたは。
As soon as the fire starts to die down,
you go looking for another spark.
戦争が下火になるとそうやってまた火種を探す
Of course, you bastard!
ったりめーよこのヤロウ。
We're warriors!
オレたちゃ戦士だゼ？
A warrior is a warrior when he's on the battlefield!
戦士は戦場にいてこそ戦士だ
But you know...
だがよ。
I heard some bad news about that.
それに関しちゃ、ちと悪いウワサを聞いたぜ
They're going to recognize King Sweyn
as the Bretwalda
今度ウェセックスの賢人会議でな。
at the next Witenagemot in Wessex.
スヴェン王がブレトワルダとして認められるそうだ
What?
はァ？
That's total surrender!
それって全面降伏じゃん
That's right. Denmark is going
to swallow England whole.
だな。デンマークがイングランドを呑み込むんだ。
The nobility want to end the war, even if it means
surrendering the throne.
貴族どもは王権を捨ててでも戦争を終わらせたいらしい
Every time I get a bad feeling about something,
why does it always come true?
悪い予感てのはどーしてこう当たるのか…
What are you going to do? Attack King Sweyn,
even if it means certain death?
どうする？玉砕覚悟でスヴェン王軍にカチ込むかい？
You idiot!
あほゥ！
I love fighting, but I hate losing!
オレァケンカは大好きだが負けるのは大嫌いだ！
When I fight, I fight to win!
やるなら勝ちに行く！
This is no fun.
つまんねーなー…
I wish the world would be at war forever.
世界中がずーっとケンカしてたらいいのになー…
It's a messenger! Is the lord here?
伝令だ！領主様はおられるか！
Anything out of the ordinary, Ear?
異常はねぇか？耳よ
There sure is. It's damn cold.
大ありだ。クソさみィぜ
The snow absorbs sounds.
雪が音を吸うんだ。
NORTH PART OF EARLDOM OF MERCIA
ASKELADD'S ARMY CONTROLLED FARM VILLAGE
さすがのオレでも聴き取れる範囲はせまくなる
Even I can't hear that far anymore.
It's better than keeping guards all over the place.
見張りをバラまくよりゃマシだ。
We can avoid giving away our position.
ここに居ることを宣伝しねぇで済む
Then do something about those guys.
なら…あいつらを何とかしろよ。
They're obviously not farmers.
っから見ても農民にゃ見えねーぞ
-Monks? Keep an eye on them, too.
-Father, forgive us.
修道士たちか。そっちも見張っとけ
…赦し給え
"Forgive us." Hear that?
赦し給え…だとよ。
Must they constantly beg for forgiveness?
あいつら、なんかある度に許しを乞わにゃなんねぇのか？
What a pain.
面倒くせぇ
Oh, God Most High,
いと高き方。
Our Father in Heaven,
天にいます我らの父よ。
please gather the souls of the villagers
ここに眠る村人たちの魂を
who lie in rest here to your side.
どうか御許にお召し下さい
Please save the souls of the men who killed
these people.
この者たちを殺めし者たちの魂をお救い下さい。
Please forgive us for our sins.
私どもの罪をお赦し下さい
This isn't the time to be praying for someone else,
you bastards.
他人のために祈ってる場合かよ、テメェら
Father.
父よ。
Can you hear my voice?
私の声はあなたの耳に届いているのでしょうか
Our Father.
我らの父よ…
You
あなたは
created us in your image.
あなたの姿に似せて私たちをお作りになった
But you didn't give us your power.
でもその力を分けては下さらなかった
Father.
父よ…
If you love both good men and bad men equally,
あなたが善き者も悪しき者も等しく愛されるというのなら、
why do you test us, despite our powerlessness?
何のために無力な私たちを試されるのですか
Father.
父よ…
Can you
私の声は
hear my voice?
あなたの耳に届いているのでしょうか
Our Father.
我らの父よ…
I doubt
私はあなたの愛を…
-your love.
-Enough!
疑っています
やめよ！
Did you say...
父を…
you doubt the Father?
疑うだと…？
And you call yourself a Christian?
You should fear the Lord!
そなた、それでもキリスト教徒か！？畏れを知るがいい！
We must not doubt the Father's love!
我らが父の愛を疑うことなどあってはならぬ！
Every father...
我が子を…
Every father loves his own child.
我が子を愛おしく思わぬ父親など…いない！
Your Highness...
殿下…
Oh! Wait!
あ…お待ちを！
Father...
父上…
An army of Danes?
デーン人の部隊！？
Really?
マジか？
Yes. That's what the message said.
は…伝令ではそのように…
They've occupied a village
at the head of the Severn River.
セヴァーン川上流の小村を占領しているらしく…
We've received a request for reinforcements
from the local lord.
地元領主から援軍の要請がきておりまして…
According to one of the villagers who survived,
生き残った村民の話によると、
the enemy has around 100 to 200 men.
敵兵はおおよそ100から200
Soldiers from neighboring areas are already
heading there,
すでに近隣の兵が向かっておるそーですが…ここは
but we wanted to ask you to come too, Thorkell,
because of your military fame.
武名轟くトルケル閣下にもぜひ…
-What do you think?
-Nothing, really.
どう思う？
どうもこうも…
There aren't a lot of Danish units who would
act alone there
この季節、その位置に単独行動のデーン人部隊など
at this time of year.
そういくつもねぇだろうよ
They feigned to go by sea,
but they're heading to Gainsborough by land.
海路と見せかけて陸路でゲインズバラへ…
They must have been snowed in and are stuck.
雪に降り込められて休息中、ってトコか？
I'm almost certain it's...
十中八九は…
Thorfinn and Canute.
トルフィンとクヌートだ
All right! Wake everyone up! Get ready to march!
いよぉし！全員起こせ！進軍用意！
And...
それと…
Hey, you.
おい、あんた
Pack us some lunch.
弁当の用意たのむぜ。
For 500 men. Five days will be enough.
500人前を～…5日分でいいや！
Five hundred?
ごっごひゃっ！？
Here we go.
よォーしよし！
This is fun. If we do this right,
面白ぇぞ。このケンカうまくすると…
we can enjoy this war for a long time!
まだまだ楽しめるかもな！
How many men are there? Ear?
何人だ、耳
Who knows? Maybe 50, or 100.
さぁな。50か100か…
They're extending their line to the east along the forest.
林づたいに東へ包囲線を伸ばしてる
They discovered us quickly.
嗅ぎつけられるのが早ェなァ。
Did we make a mistake somewhere?
どっかでヘマしたか？
I don't know...
どうだかな。
They found us. We can't change that.
とにかく見つかったもんはしょうがねェ
We're leaving?
出発ゥ！？
Tonight? That's impossible!
ムリだぜ今夜なんて！
I've only finished two sleds!
ソリはまだ2台しかできてねー。
I just started on the third one yesterday!
昨日3台目にかかったトコだ
Really? Thanks. Then finish them by tonight.
そうか。ご苦労さん。なら夜までに仕上げろ。
We'll abandon the ones we can't finish.
間に合わねぇ荷車は捨てる
I said that's impossible!
ムリだっつーの。
We only have two carpenters!
大工は2人しかいねーんだ！
The English army found us.
イングランド軍にここがバレた
-They found us?
-Yeah.
バレた！？
おーよ。
They came through the snow.
この雪かきわけて来やがった。
They must really hate the Danes.
よっぽどデーン人が憎いと見える
Impossible...
そんな…
We must hurry, or we'll miss our chance
to escape.
急がねぇと脱出の機会を失う
Understand? Hurry and finish.
わかったらちゃちゃっとやれ
Okay.
う…わ、わかった
Bjorn! Prepare the men for battle.
ビョルン。ゴロツキどもに応戦の態勢をとらせろ。
Capture their commander.
I want to find out how they found us.
指揮官は捕らえるぞ。なんでバレたか知りてェ
Understood.
了解
Wait, Bjorn.
あーっと待てビョルン
One more thing.
もうひとつ。
This is a good opportunity.
いい機会だ。
Let's do what we discussed as well.
ついでにアレ…やるぞ
They found us?
バレた！？
This is bad.
ちょっとやばいんじゃねぇか？
We'll be fine! The English are weak.
平気だろ。イングランドの兵隊は弱ェからな
No. That's not what I mean.
イヤ、そーでなくて…
I was talking about Askeladd's luck.
アシェラッドのツキの話さ
Luck?
ツキ？
First the heavy snowfall, and now this.
ドカ雪に続いてこれだ。
This is the first time his plans have ever been ruined.
あいつの計画が立て続けに狂うなんて初めてだぜ
Oh! What a tasty-looking rabbit!
ほぉ！うまそうなウサギだな。
-Are you the one who caught it, Thorfinn?
-What?
お前がとったのか？トルフィン
あァ？
Are you going to eat it alone? Are you going to roast it?
独りで食うのか？焼くのかそれ？
Why do you care?
だったらなんだよ
It's not good to eat nothing but meat!
肉だけの飯はよくないぞ。
Boil it with some vegetables!
野菜と一緒に煮込め。
I'll make some soup with that rabbit.
そのウサギはスープにしてやろう
Shut up. I can eat my own food however I want.
うるせぇな。オレの飯をどう食おうがオレの勝手だ
You're going to borrow someone's stove anyway, right?
どうせどこかでカマドを借りるんじゃろ？
Come over here!
ほれ！来い！
Your Highness! I've brought broad beans,
cabbage, and rabbit!
殿下！そら豆とキャベツとウサギです
Rabbit?
ウサギ？
Yes. Thorfinn caught it.
はい。トルフィンが捕まえまして。
I thought it would be good to add to the soup.
スープに加えたらいかがかと
Thanks.
ご苦労。
Drain the blood and remove its organs.
血を抜いて内臓を洗っておけ
The ingredients are simple, but it tastes good.
粗末な食材の割にはなかなか
It's because of the rabbit.
ウサギのおかげだ。
I've grown tired of eating salted-cured meat. Thank you.
塩漬け肉には飽いていた。礼を言うぞ
What's wrong? Don't hold back.
どうした、遠慮するな。
It's your rabbit.
そなたのウサギだ
It's good, right? Catch us a deer next time!
うまかろうが。次は鹿でもとってこい
I thought royals only did the eating.
貴族ってのは食うばかりだと思ってたぜ…
It's my hobby. I don't usually cook.
趣味だ。ふだんは作らぬし、
No one knows about it except Ragnar.
ラグナルの他は誰も知らぬ。
You can't tell anyone either, okay?
そなたも口外してはならぬぞ
There's nothing wrong with it.
別に悪かねぇだろ
A long time ago,
昔に
I cooked some cod.
タラの料理を作った時な。
It turned out well,
よい出来だったので
so I brought it to my father.
父王陛下に持っていったことがある…
But His Highness didn't eat it.
だが陛下は召し上がるどころか
He was very angry.
激しくお怒りになった
"You're the child of a king! Don't act like a slave!"
That's what he said.
“王の子が卑しき奴隷の真似事をするな”と
I wasn't supposed to cook after that.
以来僕は料理などせぬことになっている。
A king's child doesn't need to know how to do
things like this.
王の子にはこんな技など必要ないのだ
At that time,
あの頃は…
His Highness must have been very busy.
王陛下もお忙しかったのでしょう…
When this war is over, let's cook some poultry
and bring it to him.
戦が終わったら鳥料理でも作ってお持ちしましょう。
I'm sure he'd be happy.
きっと喜んで下さいます
What kind of poultry?
ナニ鳥だ？
I've never cooked poultry before.
鳥はまだ作ったことがないな
Chicken, or duck.
ニワトリでもカモでも。
Do you remember the duck you ate during Yule?
以前にユルで食べたカモを覚えておられますか？
Yes. That was delicious.
ああ。アレはうまかったな
I asked the cook for his secret.
後で料理人にコツを聞きました。
He made good use of the broth.
煮こごりを上手に使っておりましてな
The broth? I see.
煮こごりか、なるほどな
Ragnar!
ラグナ…おわ！？
You idiot! I have a message!
バカヤロ！伝令だ伝令！
What is it? What's wrong?
なんじゃ！なにがあった？
The enemy has found us.
敵に見つかったっス。
A battle has begun in the woods to the east.
東の森で戦闘がおっぱじまりました
What?
なに！？
They don't have a lot of men,
大した兵数じゃなさそうですが
but please be careful.
一応用心して下さい
What's going on?
どういうことじゃ！
We've only been in this village for ten days!
この村に潜んでまだ10日だぞ！
-How come they found us?
-How am I supposed to know?
なぜバレた！？
知るかよンなの！
What's going on?
なんということだ。
We even killed all the villagers...
村人たちを皆殺しにしてまで…！
In any case,
とにかく
we're going to move once we defeat the English.
Get ready.
イングランド兵を蹴散らしたら移動しますんでヨロシク
That's why I first said
だから
we should turn back to Wales!
はじめからウェールズに引き返せと…！
No. We're heading for Derby.
いや、向かうのはダービーす
He still wants to keep walking through
この期に及んで…
enemy lands in this situation?
まだ敵地を進むとぬかすか！？
Bring Askeladd here. Now!
アシェラッドを連れてこい！今すぐだ！
He's leading at the frontline right now.
今は前線で指揮を執ってます。
If you want to talk to him, you should go
see him yourself.
話があるならご自分で出向けばいーんじゃないスかぁ？
I'll show you the way.
案内しますよ？
Unbelievable! You men are just like your leader!
ったく！首領が首領なら部下も部下だ！
You don't have any manners!
口の利き方も知らん！
He can't even read his own luck!
己のツキの有無を見定められんで
And he's a Norse warrior?
何がノルド戦士か！
I swear on my sword, I'm going to show him
今日こそ剣にかけて愚かさを
how foolish he is today!
思い知らせてやるわい！！
Hey!
おい！
The sound of the battle is coming from that way!
ときの声はあっちから聞こえるぞ
You finally noticed? You're so slow.
やっと気づいたか。ニブいなぁあんた
What? You bastards! What are you--?
あァ！？貴様ら何を…
You bastards...
貴様ら…
Sorry, Conehead.
すまねぇなトンガリ頭。
It's orders from Askeladd.
アシェラッドの命令なんでね
Want to fight? We're okay with that.
やるかい？オレらはかまわねぇけどよ…
But you're going to die anyway.
どうせ助からねぇ
Bring Askeladd here! I have something important
to tell him.
アシェラッドをここへ呼べ…大事な話がある…
Is it your dying wish? I'll listen. Tell me.
遺言ならオレが聞くぜ。話せよ
Just bring him here!
いいから呼べ！！
It's related to His Highness the Prince.
王子殿下に関わることだ！
I need to talk to him directly.
直接話す！
Hurry!
急げ！
Let's hear your dying wish.
伺いましょう、その遺言
Shall we speak in private?
人払いしますか？
The cries stopped.
声がやんだ。
The battle is over.
戦闘が終わったな
Unbelievable.
まったく…
The soup got cold.
スープが冷めてしまったじゃないか…
I'm grateful to you.
貴殿には感謝しております。
You did a good job keeping that coward of a prince alive.
あの腰ヌケ王子をよくぞ今日まで生かして下さった
Your death will cause him to grow
そして貴殿の死が
even further.
更なる成長を促すでしょう。
I will take over that job starting today,
お役目は今日から私が引き継ぎます。
in place of you, who was
イングランド兵に殺された
"killed by the English."
貴殿のかわりにね
Swear to your god!
貴様の神に誓え…
Swear that you'll take over for me,
不足なくワシのあとを引き継ぎ…
and that...
何があろうと…
you'll protect His Highness Canute
at whatever the cost!
クヌート殿下をお守りすると…
I will protect His Highness Canute
at whatever the cost,
何があろうとクヌート殿下をお守りし
and ensure that Ragnar the warrior
did not die in vain.
戦士ラグナルの意義ある死に報いん
Are you satisfied?
ご満足かな？
It fills me with regret
口惜しや…
to leave His Highness with you.
貴様などに殿下を託そうとは…
You should hurry.
急がれたほうがいい。
You've lost a lot of blood.
血をだいぶ失っておられる
Before you reach
ゲインズバラに…
Gainsborough,
着く前に…
you should prepare yourself...
心構えを…しておけ…
The court in Jelling
イェリングの廷臣たちは今…
are fighting over who will be the next king of Denmark
次代のデンマーク王の座をめぐって
and has split into two factions.
大きく二派に分かれておる…
One of the factions picked His Highness Canute
クヌート殿下は一方の派閥の
as their leader.
旗頭にされておる
The other faction chose Canute's brother,
もう一方はクヌート様の兄君の
Harald.
ハラルド様だ…
They don't care about what
りょ、両殿下の…
either of them wants.
ご意思など関係ない…
It's just a power struggle
奸臣どもの
amongst those traitors.
勝手な勢力争いだ…
His Highness the King feared
そして王陛下は…
that the Kingdom of Denmark would be split.
デンマーク王国の分裂を恐れたのだろう…
His heart was probably already decided.
おそらくひとつの決断を内心に下された…
He decided to kill
両殿下のうち…
one of the princes.
どちらかを殺そうと…
King Sweyn decided to kill the prince?
スヴェン王が王子を！？
The reason that the king
こたび王陛下が
took the prince to the battlefield with him
殿下を戦場へ伴ったのは…
was to have the prince die in battle.
殿下を戦死させるためだ…
Be careful.
心せよ…
Prince Canute's real enemy
クヌート殿下の真の敵は…
is now
今や…
his father, King Sweyn
お父上のスヴェン王陛下、
himself.
その人なのだ…
Go into exile.
ぼ…亡命しろ。
That's the only way now.
もはやそれしかない…
In Gainsborough,
ゲインズバラで…
my brother will make preparations
ワシの弟が段取りを…
for you...
つけて…
What's going on?
でぇー…なんてこった…
You should have told me earlier.
早めに言ってくれよそーゆーことァよォ…
Please.
た…頼む…
Just one...
最後に…
last look...
一目でいい…
Let me see His Highness.
ひとめ殿下に…
To say goodbye...
お、お別れを…
No.
だめだ
Your Highness...
殿下…
Once this war is over...
戦が終わったら…
let's cook poultry together.
一緒に鳥料理でも…
I'm sure
きっと…
the king would be...
王陛下も喜んで…
happy.
くださ…